<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from several of the Protestant clergie in Cheshire, to a divine in London</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48079</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825947</idno>
  <idno type="VID">30339</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240891710</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1505A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213610</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825947</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99825947e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48079)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30339)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1796:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from several of the Protestant clergie in Cheshire, to a divine in London</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Variant: initial "W" at beginning of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Clergy --  Office --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Pas </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:30339:1"/>
            <head>A Letter from several of the Protestant Clergie IN CHESHIRE, To a Divine in LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Reverend Brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE blush when we consider how we are out-done, both in the actings and writings of the Laity of our Country; and withall when we consider how we have been scandalled by some people of this Nation, in esteeming us the onely Incendiaries of the late War in <hi>England.</hi> Truely we believe there were some Hot-spurs amongst the rest of our Function, who out of too much indiscreet zeal, might put a prejudice upon the whole Clergy, yet they taken in a right square sense, would appear to the Judicious and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, good and upright. But now admitting either, we have a greater work to do, that is, to clear our selves of the one, and make good the other with our Christian Militia. VVe look upon this our undertaking here, little inferior to that of the Holy VVar, for we are as great Champions of Christ in rooting out Heresie as Heathenism. Our hearts tend, and our bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els yern to hear that the reigning power among you have put a strength and power into their hands, that dare fight against none but Christ and his Church; that Quakers and Anabaptists should not onely be countenanced and connived at, but incouraged in their undertakings. VVe believe none of you are ignorant of what damnable bloody temper their spirits are when once heightned with a sense and knowledge of their own strength. VVe have heard of a pledge of their love a Quaker gave to a Divine in <hi>Somersetshire.</hi> Reverend, VVe shall not trouble you with Arguments to induce you, nor the rest of our Reverend Brethren, because we hope, as you cannot but be sensible how far the Almighty hath permitted Sathan in the advancing his own Kingdom amongst us, so you will assist and relieve us and your selves, both in your Pulpits and Closets. VVe do resolve to sacrifize the last and pretiousest drop of our blood in this our Countries under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking; And we do likewise conjure you all, by that promise you made at the reception of Holy Orders (not to deny Christ before men) to Preach the same. VVe need not tell you, we are all not onely obliged not to speak nor act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Christ and Holy Church, but especially to Preach it and act for it, nay in the face of the most eminent danger.</p>
            <p>We do beseech you, as you will answer it before God, as you tender the Welfare of Church and Country, not to lose a minutes opportunity of preaching the peoples Duty to them in this regard. If a Heathen thought it <hi>dulce et nobile pro patria mari,</hi> it is <hi>ter nobile &amp; dulcissimum pro Ecclesia pati.</hi> If we have begun the redemption of our Countrey, let it be your businesse to compleat it. The world will attribute the glory to you, if you'l but in this exigency of time crown this glorious work. That whereas the Church composed Common Prayers for its Country, they will now do it for us. VVe have here exprest to you the very sense of our Souls, and by the assistance of God what we do, and with the hazard of our lives and fortunes will preach and publish, as the great concern of all mankind in this Nation, that dare own the name of Christ. Let not those illiterate and phanatick opiniators, as Anabaptists and Quakers, triumph over us For believe it, they will (if Conquerors) make us all Quake, and rebaptise us in our own blood. Once again you have your dear and tender Mother the Church lying a bleeding, implores your ayd; Let her not perish under Tyranny and Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, when it is in our power to retrive her. In this work we gain a farr greater glory and reward than that Bishop who redeemed <hi>Naples</hi> from the Usurpation of <hi>Massinello.</hi> This is all, beseeching you for Gods sake, for his Churches sake, not to forget your dayly Duty, your hourly, nay to make it your street-Office, to let your flock know how much their Lives, Fortunes, and Religion is concerned, in not trusting a sword in such madmens hands, but unanimously to disarm them, and thereby redeem your Church and State from an insupportable Slavery.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:30339:2"/>
            <head>A Letter from several of the Protestant Clergie IN CHESHIRE, To a Divine in LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Reverend Brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE blush when we consider how we are out-done, both in the actings and writings of the Laity of our Country; and withall when we consider how we have been scandalled by some people of this Nation, in esteeming us the onely Incendiaries of the late War in <hi>England.</hi> Truely we believe there were some Hot-spurs amongst the rest of our Function, who out of too much indiscreet zeal, might put a prejudice upon the whole Clergy, yet they taken in a right square sense, would appear to the Judicious and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, good and upright. But now admitting either, we have a greater work to do, that is, to clear our selves of the one, and make good the other with our Christian Militia. VVe look upon this our undertaking here, little inferior to that of the Holy VVar, for we are as great Champions of Christ in rooting out Heresie as Heathenism. Our hearts tend, and our bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els yern to hear that the reigning power among you have put a strength and power into their hands, that dare fight against none but Christ and his Church; that Quakers and Anabaptists should not onely be countenanced and connived at, but incouraged in their undertakings. VVe believe none of you are ignorant of what damnable bloody temper their spirits are when once heightned with a sense and knowledge of their own strength. VVe have heard of a pledge of their love a Quaker gave to a Divine in <hi>Somersetshire.</hi> Reverend, VVe shall not trouble you with Arguments to induce you, nor the rest of our Reverend Brethren, because we hope, as you cannot but be sensible how far the Almighty hath permitted Sathan in the advancing his own Kingdom amongst us, so you will assist and relieve us and your selves, both in your Pulpits and Closets. VVe do resolve to sacrifize the last and pretiousest drop of our blood in this our Countries under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking; And we do likewise conjure you all, by that promise you made at the reception of Holy Orders (not to deny Christ before men) to Preach the same. VVe need not tell you, we are all not onely obliged not to speak nor act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Christ and Holy Church, but especially to Preach it and act for it, nay in the face of the most eminent danger.</p>
            <p>We do beseech you, as you will answer it before God, as you tender the Welfare of Church and Country, not to lose a minutes opportunity of preaching the peoples Duty to them in this regard. If a Heathen thought it <hi>dulce et nobile pro patria mari,</hi> it is <hi>ter nobile &amp; dulcissimum pro Ecclesia pati.</hi> If we have begun the redemption of our Countrey, let it be your businesse to compleat it. The world will attribute the glory to you, if you'l but in this exigency of time crown <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>this glorious work. That whereas the Church composed Common Prayers for its Country, they will now do it for us. VVe have here exprest to you the very sense of our Souls, and by the assistance of God what we do, and with the hazard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f our lives and fortunes will preach and publish, as the great concern of all mankind in this Nation, that dare own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he name of Christ. Let not those illiterate and phanatick opiniators, as Anabaptists and Quakers, triumph over us For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elieve it, they will (if Conquerors) make us all Quake, and rebaptise us in our own blood. Once again you have your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear and tender Mother the Church lying a bleeding, implores your ayd; Let her not perish under Tyranny and Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ution, when it is in our power to retrive her. In this work we gain a farr greater glory and reward than that Bishop who redeemed <hi>Naples</hi> from the Usurpation of <hi>Massinello.</hi> This is all, beseeching you for Gods sake, for his Churches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke, not to forget your dayly Duty, your hourly, nay to make it your street-Office, to let your flock know how much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir Lives, Fortunes, and Religion is concerned, in not trusting a sword in such madmens hands, but unanimously to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>sarm them, and thereby redeem your Church and State from an insupportable Slavery.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>